<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Why Not Wingnut? - personal</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/feeds/personal.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.katherineca.se/</id><updated>2022-12-07T14:32:44-05:00</updated><entry><title>Fail2ban woes</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/personal/fail2ban-woes.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-24T16:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T14:28:30-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2017-08-24:/personal/fail2ban-woes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I had a bit of a scare this morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm in a hotel in North Carolina, hundreds of miles from my server, when I try to log in and get a &amp;quot;Connection refused&amp;quot; error. Phooey. I hope the hotel wifi is just filtering port 22 for some terrible reason …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I had a bit of a scare this morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm in a hotel in North Carolina, hundreds of miles from my server, when I try to log in and get a &amp;quot;Connection refused&amp;quot; error. Phooey. I hope the hotel wifi is just filtering port 22 for some terrible reason, and hop to a friend's server over a non-standard port and I'm in. Great! I type out the connection again and...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connection refused&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hmmm. This is starting to get concerning. I briefly freak out that my server might have had a terrible accident, when I realize that all of the other services I rely on all the time are still running. Phew. Still, I don't have ssh access, and that is very troubling. I start poking around with other things and eventually unconsciously try to ssh back in to check something and to my surprise, it works! As soon as I realize what I've done, I pull up journalctl to see if sshd is going crazy and I'm met with hundreds of lines of Chinese IPs plugging away at my server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But wait! I have fail2ban installed. That should be stopping these, right? Well maybe something broke when the server was upgraded to Debian 9... and now I'm off trying to figure out what is running and where the config is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some time later, I finally have a solution. The problem (ultimately) was systemd, though not directly. I had moved this system to systemd some time early in Debian 7, which meant that the standard logging locations were still there, but no loger being written to. So fail2ban was looking for /var/log/auth.log, found a file, read it and found no problems, completely ignoring the fact that the file hadn't been written to since 2013. This isn't really fail2ban's fault, it has support for ingesting the systemd journal, but on Debian, the default backend still tries to use those files. I could set up rsyslog to start writing those files again, but I have no particular need or desire to do that outside of this program, especially as fail2ban knows how to read the journal on its own, if it's configured to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the solution is pretty simple, though it took me a while to get there. First, I had to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;apt-get&lt;/span&gt; install &lt;span class="pre"&gt;python3-systemd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;, to get the proper libraries to actually use the journal. Then, I had to have the following in my jail.local:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;[sshd]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;backend&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;systemd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also put a few other tweaks in there as my config hadn't actually moved over from the previous version, but since it's now in the jail.local instead of editing the system config, this shouldn't be a problem again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="server"></category></entry><entry><title>GrooveBot 2015</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/personal/groovebot-2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-05-11T17:28:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T14:07:06-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2015-05-11:/personal/groovebot-2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.grooveshark.com/"&gt;GrooveShark&lt;/a&gt; shut down a few days ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't really followed them much since I took over the original &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/Qalthos/groovebot"&gt;GrooveBot&lt;/a&gt;
codebase &lt;a class="reference external" href="/personal/groovebot-updates.html"&gt;sometime in 2011&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now GrooveBot's namesake is gone, which marks a neat sort of milestone for
the project. It has now outlived its inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.grooveshark.com/"&gt;GrooveShark&lt;/a&gt; shut down a few days ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't really followed them much since I took over the original &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/Qalthos/groovebot"&gt;GrooveBot&lt;/a&gt;
codebase &lt;a class="reference external" href="/personal/groovebot-updates.html"&gt;sometime in 2011&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now GrooveBot's namesake is gone, which marks a neat sort of milestone for
the project. It has now outlived its inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, that isn't what I really want to talk about today. Instead of
talking about the loss of GrooveShark, let me tell you about what GrooveBot has
gained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was last fiddling with GrooveBot sometime in 2014, I came to a sudden
realization. If I wanted to subject the people of the FOSSBox to the mad fever
dream of Smash Mouth mashups that is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://neilcic.com"&gt;Neil Cicierega&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://neilcic.com/mouthsounds"&gt;Mouth Sounds&lt;/a&gt;, I
would have to add some form of SoundCloud integration &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#need" id="footnote-reference-1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time, I was busy working on one of the issues that had been annoying me
(and others) since the bot's early beginnings, namely the lack of a permanent
queue that persisted through crashes (and live-coding restarts). Along with that
came some architectural updates that should make it easier to one day support
multiple backends at the same time, which is another longstanding issue that I
would dearly like to fix one day. Point being, I had a lot of other things I
wanted to accomplish, and not a lot of percieved benefit to stopping that and
dropping in a new backend instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward to PyCon 2015 sprints, and Neil Cicierega has not only made another
ridiculous mashup album with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://neilcic.com/mouthsilence"&gt;Mouth Silence&lt;/a&gt;, but has also been posting a
number of not-yet-albumized music to SoundCloud individually. So, I took a look
through SoundCloud's &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://developers.soundcloud.com/docs/api/guide"&gt;API&lt;/a&gt;, and went through some of GrooveBot's less atrophied
backends &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#old" id="footnote-reference-2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, and put together a new version that supports SoundCloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then I proceeded to play &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://soundcloud.com/neilcic/bustin"&gt;Bustin'&lt;/a&gt; on repeat for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="need" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#footnote-reference-1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Well, I mean, I could use the mpd backend, but without multiple
backend support, the pool of music would get stale quickly, and as much as
this is a project to force my musical tastes onto others, it is important to
me to let them do the same to me in return.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="old" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#footnote-reference-2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;The 2014 changes I mentioned were actually pretty deep in scope, and
while I am happier with where the bot is now, for a while Spotify was the
only supported backend because it was the only one in use, and the only one
that made the switch. Obviously now SoundCloud works, and I think MPD should
be working, but Pandora has been broken for years, and GrooveShark never
worked in the first place.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="groovebot"></category></entry><entry><title>Remysmoke Improving</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/personal/remysmoke-improving.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-26T03:44:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T14:07:06-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2013-07-26:/personal/remysmoke-improving.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://remysmoke.linkybook.com/"&gt;Remysmoke&lt;/a&gt; has had a few updates over the past week, and I think they've gone
pretty well. Remysmoke is now at version 1.2, here's the changelog for the past
few versions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="remysmoke-1-0"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Remysmoke 1.0&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moved graphs from tw2-protoviz to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pygal.org/"&gt;pygal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moved smoke input form from tw2-forms to hand-crafted HTML5 …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://remysmoke.linkybook.com/"&gt;Remysmoke&lt;/a&gt; has had a few updates over the past week, and I think they've gone
pretty well. Remysmoke is now at version 1.2, here's the changelog for the past
few versions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="remysmoke-1-0"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Remysmoke 1.0&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moved graphs from tw2-protoviz to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pygal.org/"&gt;pygal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moved smoke input form from tw2-forms to hand-crafted HTML5 forms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completely removed Toscawidgets and ToscaWidgets2 from Remysmoke (including
some very old boilerplate TurboGears code).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="remysmoke-1-1"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Remysmoke 1.1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Updated codebase to TurboGears 2.3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Redeployed Remysmoke on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://openshift.com/"&gt;OpenShift&lt;/a&gt; Python 2.7 Cartridge (was Python 2.6).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="remysmoke-1-2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Remysmoke 1.2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cleaned up login and smoke forms to be more consistent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Themed form checkboxes to be consistent with the rest of the UI.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Added new theming for disabled input boxes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Added new 'unsmoke' option, allowing a user to attest that they have not
smoked that day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remysmoke 1.2 went live late last night, and a  hotfix 1.2.1 will be up shortly
with an OpenShift-specific patch dealing with overriding the database location
at runtime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="remysmoke"></category></entry><entry><title>Recent Projects: Groovebot</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/personal/recent-projects-groovebot.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-07-24T18:47:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T14:32:44-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2012-07-24:/personal/recent-projects-groovebot.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the first of a number of posts meant to overview the things I've
been doing recently. First up on the list is the long-overdue
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/Qalthos/groovebot"&gt;Groovebot&lt;/a&gt; update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before this summer, Groovebot 'worked' on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://spotify.com/"&gt;Spotify&lt;/a&gt;, and also had a
fairly useful but under-tested &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_Player_Daemon"&gt;MPD&lt;/a&gt; backend that worked for me when …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the first of a number of posts meant to overview the things I've
been doing recently. First up on the list is the long-overdue
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/Qalthos/groovebot"&gt;Groovebot&lt;/a&gt; update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before this summer, Groovebot 'worked' on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://spotify.com/"&gt;Spotify&lt;/a&gt;, and also had a
fairly useful but under-tested &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_Player_Daemon"&gt;MPD&lt;/a&gt; backend that worked for me when I
could get MPD running properly. Unfortunately, I no longer had an active
Spotify subscription, which meant that I couldn't use the Spotify
backend, and I had moved off of RIT's campus, meaning I no longer had a
~100Mb connection to my fileserver, so streaming files that way was more
problematic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While looking around for other things I could use to get Groovebot
running on, I rediscovered &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://kevinmehall.net/p/pithos/"&gt;Pithos&lt;/a&gt;, a Python frontend to Pandora.
Using Pithos as an authenticator, I could get URLs to music files that I
could play if I could figure out how to play them in Python. As a
temporary test, I just sent them to mplayer to play the files. This
worked well enough, but had the same problem I had encountered with
Spotify, namely that I could not get a callback properly positioned to
fire when the song finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put the project aside for a time, until &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.jlewopensource.com/"&gt;Justin&lt;/a&gt; pointed out
GStreamer is made to do this sort of thing. With this in mind, I took
another look at the task, first trying to run GStreamer in its own event
loop on top of Twisted, then giving up and processing events on a tick.
This means I have to respond to every event GStreamer throws out (which
is a fair number of them), but most of them can be thrown out without
looking at them. Some more tweaking later, and PandBot was born, able to
connect to a user's Pandora station, play music, and thumb songs up or
down based on user response in the IRC channel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, I had been writing new bots each time I added a new
backend, with a lot of repeated code in each, leading to subtle bugs and
API implementations that were slowly drifting apart based on individual
needs. This made me a little annoyed, but I didn't have any particular
need to fix it, so I left it alone. Until an accidental click around the
Spotify website left me with another Premium subscription (and $10
poorer...) I poked around on SpotBot to see if it still worked. Turns
out it did... just not on the DJ computer in the FOSSBox. Turns out that
spytify, the python bindings for &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://despotify.se/"&gt;despotify&lt;/a&gt; have gotten a little stale
in the interim, and no longer compile with modern versions of Cython.
This meant I should probably break down and get an API key from Spotify
and use the proper official API instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in working on MPD and Pandora bots in the meantime had given me
a number of ideas and fixes that would be problematic to port back to
Spotify, which meant I had finally gotten an excuse to try to merge the
three separate codebases into one unified version. Starting with MPD and
Pandora, I merged the files and ran the result through a three-way diff,
trying to identify important parts of each bot to make sure each worked
properly after the merge. Next, I looked into the architecture of
pyspotify, and immediately ran into some trouble. pyspotify works
differently to the backends I had been used to, having its own threading
I would need to juggle alongside my own. Additionally, the code is not
thread safe, which is a problem with the heavily-threaded Groovebot
code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now, the status is that we are down to two bots. One is the ancient
Grooveshark code that is in need of updating and integrating with the
second bot. This second bot has all the work I've been doing lately and,
some few remaining problems aside, mostly work. Ideally, I will soon
have a better host for the bot that will let me run Spotify, but for now
Pandora is working well enough.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="groovebot"></category></entry><entry><title>OpenShift Troubles</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/personal/openshift-troubles.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-02-03T06:47:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T14:07:06-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2012-02-03:/personal/openshift-troubles.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I've been playing with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://openshift.redhat.com/"&gt;OpenShift&lt;/a&gt;, a new(ish) service from
Red Hat as a sort of 'push to cloud' deployment strategy. It's
interesting for people like me who can whip up a site quick, but don't
necessarily have the framework in place to host it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to my work …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I've been playing with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://openshift.redhat.com/"&gt;OpenShift&lt;/a&gt;, a new(ish) service from
Red Hat as a sort of 'push to cloud' deployment strategy. It's
interesting for people like me who can whip up a site quick, but don't
necessarily have the framework in place to host it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to my work on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://civx.us/"&gt;CIVX&lt;/a&gt;, I've gotten pretty familiar with
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://turbogears.org/"&gt;TurboGears&lt;/a&gt;, and the idea of being able to take a site like that and
run it without having to set up apache or fiddle with paster sounded
real nice. Unfortunately, it was not so simple as it seems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First up was to get something, anything, running. For a while, OpenShift
was throwing a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/girliemac/6509400855/in/set-72157628409467125"&gt;500 error&lt;/a&gt; when you tried to get a new application
registered. A brief poke into their IRC told had them aware of the
problem and it was fixed shortly. Next came the other part that should
have been easy, running TurboGears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lewk.org/"&gt;Luke&lt;/a&gt; our favorite wizard around these parts, wrote a bit of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/lmacken/openshift-quickstarter"&gt;code&lt;/a&gt;
to get most of the available applications up and running without too
much effort, including the currently unsupported TurboGears. Running
this went off without a problem, but the resulting site gave me another
happy 500 error. After a consult with Remy, we determined there were
some missing version requirements that kept the site from running. After
pulling those edits out of his repo and moving them upstream to Luke's,
I had a working default TurboGears site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until I tried to log in. Then I got another 500 error.
I was beginning to get used to this, but it was still annoying to make a
small change, then push it to the server and wait for the server to
update the settings before I could test it. Even more fun was the
occasional &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/girliemac/6540643319/in/set-72157628409467125/"&gt;503 error&lt;/a&gt; when OpenShift couldn't keep up with my rapidly
building and tearing down sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feeling that that was going to be a project by itself, I set about
moving all my non-db-interfacing files to this new repository. The
prebuilt version assumes that the site internally is named tg2app, and I
was having trouble convincing it to go by anything else. Eventually I
just decided to move files across one by one; first the templates that
don't care what they're named, then the root controller, than the new
model and widget. A lot of frustration, many &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/girliemac/6508023617/in/set-72157628409467125"&gt;403&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/girliemac/6508022985/in/set-72157628409467125/"&gt;404&lt;/a&gt; errors
later, I had something that pretended to work as long as I didn't use
the database. But since the database is kind of the point of the site I
was building, this was not exactly acceptable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So back to the drawing board then. I had a hunch something was wrong
when I saw SQLAlchemy errors scroll by every time I reloaded the site.
My best guess is that SQLAlchemy is failing to create the tables needed
to run the site and continuing on blindly. Once I realized that, I
dumped a test db from my local copy to the MySQL db, and suddenly
everything was working. Or almost everything, anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could read form the db fine, but any time I tried to modify it, I got
another dreaded 500 error. I poked into everything I could find to try
to figure out where it was failing, and finally determined it couldn't
be on my end, as my local copy worked just as expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally I stumbled across the answer, almost accidentally. When I moved
the db from local sqlite to MySQL, I failed to set the auto increment
setting on the id of my new databases, so when I neglected to provide an
id for the new entries I was making, MySQL quite rightly complained at
me. Unfortunately, since I can't find how to re-enable debug mode (nor
should I really try), I wasn't getting any good error messages.
So what is the site that has been giving me all these troubles? It's a
little site I set up to publicly shame Remy into stopping smoking:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://remysmoke-qalthos.rhcloud.com/"&gt;remysmoke-qalthos.rhcloud.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="FLOSS-seminar"></category><category term="openshift"></category></entry><entry><title>Openshift Troubles Continued</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/personal/openshift-troubles-continued.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-02-03T06:47:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T14:32:28-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2012-02-03:/personal/openshift-troubles-continued.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I figured out the problem I was having with OpenShift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, I didn't pay enough attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For reference, when moving an existing TurboGears app to OpenShift, make
sure you add the changes in config/app_cfg.py&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as I saw that, I felt really silly for …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I figured out the problem I was having with OpenShift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, I didn't pay enough attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For reference, when moving an existing TurboGears app to OpenShift, make
sure you add the changes in config/app_cfg.py&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as I saw that, I felt really silly for missing it. I was so sure
that I had gotten all the relevant changes, but apparently I somehow
missed this file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More detailed directions coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="FLOSS-seminar"></category><category term="openshift"></category></entry><entry><title>GrooveBot updates</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/personal/groovebot-updates.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-09-28T01:28:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T14:07:06-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2011-09-28:/personal/groovebot-updates.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I'm going to talk about something a bit more understandable, I
hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back around the summer of 2010, the FOSSBox wanted some ambient music to
play in the background. One of the things we wanted was a way to have
control over the songs played be available to anyone …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I'm going to talk about something a bit more understandable, I
hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back around the summer of 2010, the FOSSBox wanted some ambient music to
play in the background. One of the things we wanted was a way to have
control over the songs played be available to anyone, even if they
weren't here to listen with us. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jlewopensource.com/"&gt;Jlew&lt;/a&gt; was working on some IRC bots at
the time, so he wrote up a bot that could hook into the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.grooveshark.com/"&gt;GrooveShark&lt;/a&gt;
API and play music that users requested through IRC. It was cool, when
it worked, and it was fun having community control over song selections,
even when that sometimes led to a bit of musical griefing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then GrooveShark kept changing it's API without warning, then they
changed their pricing for access to said API, and then the bot stopped
working. Plans to build a more robust bot around &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://gitorious.org/jlew/groovebot"&gt;GrooveBot&lt;/a&gt;, as it was
now called, were scrapped, and the FOSSBox was quiet once more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://turntable.fm/"&gt;turntable.fm&lt;/a&gt; happened. While we are not their optimal use-case,
it did allow us a measure of community choice in our songs, and
generally got us back to playing some sweet tunes while we work, with
the added bonus that anyone could run it, not just people with premium
access. Everything was pretty good, all things considered, and we could
continue on with our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except for one thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now with GrooveBot, you could send all kinds of commands to the bot and
it would tell you what songs were playing, queue additional songs, pause
or resume playback, and so on, all from the IRC windows we were already
using to communicate with people outside of the area. I don't expect any
of this to be available for Turntable any time soon, but there is one
function that I have sorely missed. And that is the ability to change
the volume from my computer without having to get up and manually prod
whoever's running the audio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now there is a stripped version of GrooveBot on gitorious called
volbot, and all he does is respond to requests to change the volume.
Hopefully, when a new, free music API becomes available that we can hook
into, it should be easier to reimplement those functions in a more
general way so that multiple backends can be used for a more varied
music experience. And then we can get back to the OS grooving.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="groovebot"></category></entry><entry><title>pyDex 1.0</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/personal/pydex-10.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-05-08T03:19:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T14:07:06-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2011-05-08:/personal/pydex-10.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;And in mostly unrelated but terribly belated news, I finally released
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://gitorious.org/pydex"&gt;pyDex 1.0&lt;/a&gt; this morning. Black/White pokedex, new config system, baby
pokemon, and game detection, are all new features introduced in this
version. Old configs should get read properly and get seamlessly updated
to the new version, though …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;And in mostly unrelated but terribly belated news, I finally released
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://gitorious.org/pydex"&gt;pyDex 1.0&lt;/a&gt; this morning. Black/White pokedex, new config system, baby
pokemon, and game detection, are all new features introduced in this
version. Old configs should get read properly and get seamlessly updated
to the new version, though there may be a few bugs in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="pyDex"></category></entry><entry><title>Killer Bunnies and the Towering Draw Pile</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/personal/killer-bunnies-and-the-towering-draw-pile.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-01-23T07:12:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T14:07:06-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2011-01-23:/personal/killer-bunnies-and-the-towering-draw-pile.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There was a hackathon Friday night, and a write-up is coming soon, but
first a bit of random chatter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have, for a few years, been collecting the various pieces that make up
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/3699/killer-bunnies-and-the-quest-for-the-magic-carrot"&gt;Killer Bunnies and the Quest for the Magic Carrot&lt;/a&gt;. For Christmas, I
received the Stainless Steel booster …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There was a hackathon Friday night, and a write-up is coming soon, but
first a bit of random chatter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have, for a few years, been collecting the various pieces that make up
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/3699/killer-bunnies-and-the-quest-for-the-magic-carrot"&gt;Killer Bunnies and the Quest for the Magic Carrot&lt;/a&gt;. For Christmas, I
received the Stainless Steel booster pack, leaving me one short (Ominous
Onyx) of completing the game's many many expansion packs. In total, my
game had over 650 cards and was disturbingly fun to play.
Yesterday, I was surprised upon reaching my friend Eric's apartment to
be greeted with not just one, but two new expansions, one of which I
didn't even know existed. I am now the owner of not just the Ominous
Onyx booster pack, but also the mysterious new Chocolate pack, adding in
many of the hard-to-find promo cards that Playroom has put out over the
years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We put together the full game, now consisting of 770 playable cards, 11
dice, 9 pawns, a large cardboard ball, and various plastic tokens and
stands to help try and make sense of all the nonsense. The draw pile
stacks over a foot high thanks to the thick card construction, and
shuffling amounts to little more than a best-effort situation. The game
is frankly insane and a blast to play, with a breadth of randomness not
normally found in such games. While strategy is important, one can
switch freely between winning and losing with a few short turns, and
often quite frequently does. The game is long enough to be satisfying,
but not so long as to drag on, (as long as people are paying attention)
and the variety and humor in the cards keeps the game fresh play after
play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, my game is not quite complete. One more add-on remains, though
not really a necessary one. A spin-off game called Kinder Bunnies also
exists, aimed at a younger audience with streamlined rules and
simplified gameplay. It is also completely compatible with the main
Killer Bunnies game, with a few cards directly referencing Kinder
Bunnies from Killer Bunnies. it also would add another ten &amp;quot;Magic
Carrots&amp;quot; to the game, which are a sort of victory point mechanism, where
once all the Magic Carrots have been picked up, the game ends. Thus, the
addition would extend gameplay a bit more and provide new challenges for
longtime players (not to mention many more dice to play with).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that's how I spent my weekend apart from coding like a superstar. But
don't worry, I'll get to that soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="games"></category></entry><entry><title>pyDex on Sugar</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/personal/pydex-on-sugar.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-01-19T23:51:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T14:07:06-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2011-01-19:/personal/pydex-on-sugar.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A warning, this gets very technical with lots of acronyms and jargon.
tl;dr: I have a new pyDex branch which *should* run on the OLPC
A few days ago, I decided I'd finally see how well pyDex runs on the
OLPC. Turns out, it runs pretty well, which isn't …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A warning, this gets very technical with lots of acronyms and jargon.
tl;dr: I have a new pyDex branch which *should* run on the OLPC
A few days ago, I decided I'd finally see how well pyDex runs on the
OLPC. Turns out, it runs pretty well, which isn't too surprising as it
is written in pure pyGTK and Glade, both of which are well supported in
Sugar.
So today, I loaded up my dev files and set to work. First, though, I had
to clean up my dev branch and finish committing the few hacks I had
accumulated over the last few months. I finally fixed the zero index bug
and found I had a problem in my new scraper that was causing all the
evolution problems. In any case, that's all fixed, so my dev branch is
nice and clean and almost ready for the Black/White release in a few
weeks.
Getting back to Sugar, I finally found &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://magazine.redhat.com/2007/04/26/building-the-xo-porting-a-pygtk-game-to-sugar-part-two/"&gt;a good tutorial&lt;/a&gt; on *porting*
a pyGTK program rather than writing a new one. While admittedly I
haven't looked very hard, I had had a bit of a problem getting past the
example activity before, probably due to my use of Glade as I cannot
replace my top window as easily when it is automatically pulled from
Glade's XML and I really don't feel like defining everything in code.
The most useful thing I found in this tutorial is sending different
parents to the main panel depending on where it is called from. So if we
call the program normally, main_window is still loaded from Glade, but
if Sugar loads it, we use their prebuilt panel.
It still needs to be tested, and I need to add actual activity
information (and an icon eventually), but I think it should work. I'll
probably get to test it sometime this weekend, maybe even turn it into a
real activity by then. This is still just a small project, and I doubt
it will ever go up on Sugar's activities site, but it has given me a
much better understanding about how non-pygame activities work.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="sugar"></category><category term="pyDex"></category></entry><entry><title>Huzzah!</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/personal/huzzah.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-09-06T17:57:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T14:07:06-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2010-09-06:/personal/huzzah.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here we are, back at the beginning of another school year. It's going to
be interesting, I'm still pretty laid back from Fan Expo Canada in
Toronto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My new monitor finally arrived. Well, it arrived Saturday, but the RIT
post office isn't open on weekends over breaks, so I had …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here we are, back at the beginning of another school year. It's going to
be interesting, I'm still pretty laid back from Fan Expo Canada in
Toronto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My new monitor finally arrived. Well, it arrived Saturday, but the RIT
post office isn't open on weekends over breaks, so I had to wait until
this morning. Luckily, it seems that the stand on my last monitor which
made me love it so much is a standard VESA mount, so I detached it from
my old monitor, removed the sad excuse of a stand from my new monitor,
and now have a beautiful new screen on the beautiful old stand. The new
monitor, meanwhile, being an LED-backlit model, is much lighter now than
it's stand. The speakers seem okay, although they're on the back of the
monitor (no doubt meant to reflect off the wall behind them) so if I
want to blast music, I'll just end up blasting Justin instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I now have two monitors, though I don't know if I'm keeping the
ancient 15&amp;quot; LCD from home that was serving as a spare. We'll see. In the
meantime, Minecraft looks better than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="hardware"></category></entry><entry><title>Writing and Me</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/personal/writing-and-me.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-07-21T04:13:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T14:07:06-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2010-07-21:/personal/writing-and-me.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am not a writer. Had things progressed differently, I might have tried
it. I do enjoy the writing process. One important problem is that I hate
revision. I start from a theoretical perfect model, and slowly write it
out, far slower than my brain, which can race ahead to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am not a writer. Had things progressed differently, I might have tried
it. I do enjoy the writing process. One important problem is that I hate
revision. I start from a theoretical perfect model, and slowly write it
out, far slower than my brain, which can race ahead to new, more
exciting topics, while I still need to actually write what has been
planned out before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, I am a programmer. Really, the two are not very different. In
programming, however, your audience is a computer, and the computer is
far less forgiving of unclear communication. I'm not talking about typos
or misplaced parentheses here, but in the ability of the writer to
convey their ideas to the audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programming generally has a very strict syntax compared to speech. Words
generally have only one meaning, and if they have more than one, it is
immediately obvious which one is meant in any situation. Human
communication, on the other hand, has shades of meaning, imagery, and
all sorts of other trickery to say the same thing in many ways. Years of
programming has left my vocabulary a bit dry, opting for specific,
technical jargon rather than the more general, descriptive prose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it another way, if my writings were computer code, none of them
would compile. But then, none of my real code does either, not on the
first try. The compiler rejects a statement here or there, and when it
finally runs, the output is all wrong. So I tweak the code, simplify and
break down long statements, and try to say exactly what I mean.
Eventually, the code compiles and runs, and does exactly what I want it
to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does this relate to being a writer? Well, I follow mostly the same
pattern in my writing. The only difference is that I do it without a
compiler. I have learned long ago that self-correction is often useless
for me, I tend to make the same mistakes while reading as I did writing
it. My best writing comes form when I *do* have a compiler of sorts;
school assignments where each revision compiles a little further with my
teacher, and more meaning comes through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I do not write regularly anymore. The days of required
writing are almost gone, and I have yet to find a compiler for writing
which works as well as my teachers. Add to that my dislike of revision
without glaring errors to fix, and my personal writing tends to throw
parsing errors in anyone who isn't me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully I'll get better at this. At the very least I hope to catch the
common mistakes here.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="introspective"></category></entry><entry><title>pyDex Progress</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/personal/pydex-progress.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-07-10T16:51:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T14:07:06-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2010-07-10:/personal/pydex-progress.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've finally gotten around to staging and committing a few enhancements
to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://gitorious.org/pydex"&gt;pydex repository&lt;/a&gt;. The more advanced stuff like Isshu pokemon
and the new file format are still in limbo, naturally, and won't get
moved to master any time soon since they make older files incompatible,
though I hope …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've finally gotten around to staging and committing a few enhancements
to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://gitorious.org/pydex"&gt;pydex repository&lt;/a&gt;. The more advanced stuff like Isshu pokemon
and the new file format are still in limbo, naturally, and won't get
moved to master any time soon since they make older files incompatible,
though I hope to at least be able to read them for the time being.
I'm also beginning to wonder about dynamically limiting the National
Pokedex based on the game setting, once that actually does something.
I've only played Gen IV extensively, but after loading up Yellow on a
whim, I see how this could be useful. But I'm more concerned with
bugfixing 1.0 so that it can see the light of day than tacking on more
features right now.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="pyDex"></category></entry></feed>