<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Why Not Wingnut? - Boston</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/feeds/tag/boston.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.katherineca.se/</id><updated>2022-12-07T14:07:06-05:00</updated><entry><title>Boston</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/civx/boston.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-01-23T07:14:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T14:07:06-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2011-01-23:/civx/boston.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So here we are in OLPC HQ, right in the middle of MIT. It's pretty sweet
having &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lewk.org/"&gt;Luke&lt;/a&gt; around again to hack CIVX with us.
I've had a lot to do in the past few days. Remy's been showing me
scrapers and models, and I've been helping transition &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://foss.rit.edu/user/17"&gt;Kate's&lt;/a&gt; people …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So here we are in OLPC HQ, right in the middle of MIT. It's pretty sweet
having &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lewk.org/"&gt;Luke&lt;/a&gt; around again to hack CIVX with us.
I've had a lot to do in the past few days. Remy's been showing me
scrapers and models, and I've been helping transition &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://foss.rit.edu/user/17"&gt;Kate's&lt;/a&gt; people
dashboard into an integrated component or integrating &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://rebeccanatalie.com/"&gt;Rebecca's&lt;/a&gt; theme
changes on the side. It's been hectic and fun and tough, but I finally
feel like I'm contributing to a project, something with substance and
goals, not just writing code to accomplish a task like some of my
previous co-ops. Being in a team this large helps, especially when we
pull in outside help like Luke, but I think it's mainly Remy's
infectious excitement for the project. When he gets down to work, one
can't help but feel his vision and be excited for the possibilities.
Unfortunately, that means I had precious little time to pay attention to
the other teams. Three separate groups hacking away at their own
projects, tossing ideas about and getting input from a few members
upstream, not to mention the whole OLPC offices around the corner- this
was a right proper hackathon, and something that makes me excited for the
future of these projects.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="CIVX"></category><category term="peopledashboard"></category><category term="hackathon"></category><category term="widgets"></category><category term="Boston"></category></entry></feed>