<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Why Not Wingnut? - introspective</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/feeds/tag/introspective.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.katherineca.se/</id><updated>2022-12-07T17:00:07-05:00</updated><entry><title>Hello Again</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/personal/hello-again.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-12-07T16:08:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T17:00:07-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2022-12-07:/personal/hello-again.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've thought a lot about writing this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also thought a lot about &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; writing it, and just leaving the whole thing
up as a semipermanent memorial to he-who-never-really-was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then I got to fixing up the domain redirects, and then I noticed the content
errors, and got around …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've thought a lot about writing this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also thought a lot about &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; writing it, and just leaving the whole thing
up as a semipermanent memorial to he-who-never-really-was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then I got to fixing up the domain redirects, and then I noticed the content
errors, and got around to fixing rather a lot of things that had piled up in the
last nine years since I'd last updated this and that meant taking some time to
read some of the posts I had made back in the FOSS&amp;#64;RIT days. And it really
crystalized a few things for me — and reinforced the idea that after all that
has changed, I am still me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you've been here before, please take note of the new name and location,
and welcome back. If you're new here, well, I really don't know what to tell
you. I can't say that I intend to update this ever again, but at least I will
feel at home if I do.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="blog"></category><category term="introspective"></category></entry><entry><title>Writing and Me</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/personal/writing-and-me.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-07-21T04:13:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T14:07:06-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2010-07-21:/personal/writing-and-me.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am not a writer. Had things progressed differently, I might have tried
it. I do enjoy the writing process. One important problem is that I hate
revision. I start from a theoretical perfect model, and slowly write it
out, far slower than my brain, which can race ahead to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am not a writer. Had things progressed differently, I might have tried
it. I do enjoy the writing process. One important problem is that I hate
revision. I start from a theoretical perfect model, and slowly write it
out, far slower than my brain, which can race ahead to new, more
exciting topics, while I still need to actually write what has been
planned out before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, I am a programmer. Really, the two are not very different. In
programming, however, your audience is a computer, and the computer is
far less forgiving of unclear communication. I'm not talking about typos
or misplaced parentheses here, but in the ability of the writer to
convey their ideas to the audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programming generally has a very strict syntax compared to speech. Words
generally have only one meaning, and if they have more than one, it is
immediately obvious which one is meant in any situation. Human
communication, on the other hand, has shades of meaning, imagery, and
all sorts of other trickery to say the same thing in many ways. Years of
programming has left my vocabulary a bit dry, opting for specific,
technical jargon rather than the more general, descriptive prose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it another way, if my writings were computer code, none of them
would compile. But then, none of my real code does either, not on the
first try. The compiler rejects a statement here or there, and when it
finally runs, the output is all wrong. So I tweak the code, simplify and
break down long statements, and try to say exactly what I mean.
Eventually, the code compiles and runs, and does exactly what I want it
to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does this relate to being a writer? Well, I follow mostly the same
pattern in my writing. The only difference is that I do it without a
compiler. I have learned long ago that self-correction is often useless
for me, I tend to make the same mistakes while reading as I did writing
it. My best writing comes form when I *do* have a compiler of sorts;
school assignments where each revision compiles a little further with my
teacher, and more meaning comes through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I do not write regularly anymore. The days of required
writing are almost gone, and I have yet to find a compiler for writing
which works as well as my teachers. Add to that my dislike of revision
without glaring errors to fix, and my personal writing tends to throw
parsing errors in anyone who isn't me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully I'll get better at this. At the very least I hope to catch the
common mistakes here.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="introspective"></category></entry></feed>