<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Why Not Wingnut? - journalism</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/feeds/tag/journalism.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.katherineca.se/</id><updated>2022-12-07T15:50:42-05:00</updated><entry><title>Recent Projects: Democrat &amp; Chronicle</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/fossrit/recent-projects-democrat-chronicle.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-08-22T22:16:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T14:32:12-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2012-08-22:/fossrit/recent-projects-democrat-chronicle.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the new projects I had this summer was a project proposed by the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.democratandchronicle.com/"&gt;Democrat &amp;amp; Chronicle&lt;/a&gt;. The project involved access to a selection of
emails sent to the Greece school district in the wake of the YouTube
video involving several of their students. The idea was that we would …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the new projects I had this summer was a project proposed by the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.democratandchronicle.com/"&gt;Democrat &amp;amp; Chronicle&lt;/a&gt;. The project involved access to a selection of
emails sent to the Greece school district in the wake of the YouTube
video involving several of their students. The idea was that we would
get a dump of email bodies and try to glean some information out of
them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first hurdle, unfortunately, was getting at the information. Shortly
after we were approached with the request, I received an Access file
containing around 5000 email bodies to go through. Being what we are,
most of the resources in the FOSSBox are oriented around Linux, and no
one about had a copy of Access installed to get the data into a more
friendly format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In theory, there are ODBC drivers for access databases, just like there
are for any other database system. In practice, however, they seem to
only exist for Windows machines which, while not surprising, was
disappointing. This led me to dig out an old VirtualBox VM with Windows
XP on it, install the Access drivers from Microsoft, and throw
LibreOffice on it, too. There's other ways I could have gotten this done
instead of LibreOffice, but I was still hoping this could be a simple
action at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LibreOffice Base eventually got into the Access file, but then the
troubles started again. It initially prompted me to save a LibreOffice
database file, which sounded great to me... it could export it
immediately, then I could copy it over and finish the task in Linux.
Unfortunately, all this file did was create a small wrapper around the
Access file, telling LibreOffice where the file was located, and what
was needed to open it. So now I was back to trying to export the data.
LibreOffice, though, was not willing to play along. I admit I am less
than familiar with the Base component of LibreOffice, however some
exploration and more searching online led me to believe I could not do
the simple translation of data from one format to another from within
Base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, I needed to select the table I was interested in (the only
table in the database), tell LibreOffice to copy the table, then open a
new spreadsheet in LibreOffice Calc and save the data that way. While
this makes some sense to me (Base being simply for basic interaction
with databases, Calc for manipulating raw data), I was dismayed that I
could not find some way to export a single table to a common data
format, like CSV, instead of having to go through yet another step. In
any case, once I dumped the data into Calc, I could easily save it to
CSV, drop that into my real computer, stop the VM, and get to work for
real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end result is &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/Qalthos/mail_scrape"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. I'm not sure it will ever be of any
particular use to anyone other than myself to remind me how to use the
Python NLTK module (whose documentation seems to be geared more towards
researchers than those already familiar with Python), and is hardcoded
to certain facets of the data I was given, but it does manage to do a
few things, and at each step it dumps the state of the data to a file so
I can inspect the process and consider possible improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="FOSS@RIT"></category><category term="journalism"></category><category term="data alchemy"></category></entry><entry><title>Imagine RIT 2011</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/fossrit/imagine-rit-2011.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-05-08T03:16:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T14:07:06-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2011-05-08:/fossrit/imagine-rit-2011.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I've been absent for a while lately, but with good reason. I've been
preparing for Imagine RIT, which was held earlier today.
After pulling possibly my longest day's hack yesterday (1pm to 4am,
approximately), I woke up at 9 and headed over to the Innovation Center
to talk to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I've been absent for a while lately, but with good reason. I've been
preparing for Imagine RIT, which was held earlier today.
After pulling possibly my longest day's hack yesterday (1pm to 4am,
approximately), I woke up at 9 and headed over to the Innovation Center
to talk to people about FOSS. All day long, the FOSSBox was filled with
curious people, looking to find out what it is we did. We had kids
poking around on the OLPCs, checking out our software, and occasionally
getting lost opening new programs. Every time I finished showing a group
around all the different projects hosted in the FOSSBox, a brand new
group would appear and start asking questions. It was tiring, especially
on about three hours of sleep, but it was quite fun and exciting showing
off our work to new people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of particular interest was Lemonade Stand, which seemed to excite many
of the children who came around. Most seemed to pick up the game with
minimal instruction (though it helped that by now I know very well which
areas to explain... they should get tightened in the future) and most
had lots of fun despite the large quantities of math involved.
And the backdrop to all this was &lt;a class="reference external" href="rise.rit.edu"&gt;Rise Above the Crowd&lt;/a&gt;, the project I
was spending so much time polishing yesterday. I don't know if I could
explain what exactly Rise is, other than a real-time journalism and news
collection framework, which doesn't really explain anything. Basically,
users submit stories and photos to Rise, which in turn keep track of
popular and recent content and display this information to strategically
placed screens throughout the campus. After a few hiccoughs, the servers
were online and serving data to the public, who then voted on their
favorite stories. At the FOSSBOX, we had the projector set up serving
the HD display mode so people could see what was current while they were
there. Since I was the one most familiar with the system at the time, I
tried to field any questions that popped up at the time to the best of
my knowledge, though sometimes that wasn't much help. As the day
progressed, we uncovered a few new bugs in the new system, and have some
new tasks before the final release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, a very exciting and fun weekend. We made a few contacts,
introduced a few more people to FOSS&amp;#64;RIT, and gave away at least 40
LiveCDs. I think that qualifies as quite a success.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="FOSS@RIT"></category><category term="journalism"></category><category term="lemonade"></category><category term="sugar"></category><category term="Rise"></category><category term="OPL"></category></entry><entry><title>Election Aftermath</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/fossrit/election-aftermath.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-03-29T02:59:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T15:49:52-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2011-03-29:/fossrit/election-aftermath.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So the election was almost a week ago. Here's how our little experiment
turned out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image0" src="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1386/5143595646_9e4e56f556.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evening started out rather slowly, with information trickling in
about races that were all but confirmed. We had the Innovation Center's
display set up with various maps and information, and my page in the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So the election was almost a week ago. Here's how our little experiment
turned out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image0" src="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1386/5143595646_9e4e56f556.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evening started out rather slowly, with information trickling in
about races that were all but confirmed. We had the Innovation Center's
display set up with various maps and information, and my page in the
center in five columns, all showing zero votes.
We waited until the polls closed at 9PM, and then we waited some more
for the information to travel to the Board of Elections and make it onto
the XML file. Even at this point, I still didn't know if the scraper was
going to work, so I was checking the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://66.192.47.50/flashresults.html"&gt;official unofficial results page&lt;/a&gt;
to make sure they didn't have anything we didn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the first results popped on the screen, it was amazing. When
results kept pouring in, it was even more impressive. When we finally
figured out that all those numbers were wrong, it was time to start
getting things fixed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were several differences from what the Canadian data had led me to
expect, and so I spent most of the night fixing small problems as they
showed up. First, votes in NYS are tallied by party, even if multiple
parties are running the same candidate. This was quite different from
what I had been led to expect, and so the numbers we started out with
were quite.. bizarre. Before we realized what was going on, it looked
like Paladino was beating Cuomo in Monroe County almost 4 to 1. Checking
back with the flash page revealed that I was only counting one party for
each candidate, and whichever came last would show up on the screen. I
had to keep a running count for each candidate rather than throwing out
old data when going through the file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having fixed that, and seeing that the numbers now matched what was
coming out of the flash page, I settled back down and watched the third
parties fight for 50,000 votes. That is, until someone pointed out to me
that Andrew Cuomo was currently listed with 1.7 million votes for Monroe
County alone. Seeing as how the total population of the area is only
about 1 million, there was clearly something wrong. It seems that in my
haste to keep count of how many votes a candidate got from each party, I
was not clearing these numbers once the file was done being read. This
was probably the hardest fix I had to make during the night, as it broke
some of the models I had naively put forth on how the program should
run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I eventually ended up with a workable solution, though I was sad to see
the third party numbers were much lower now. There remained only one
small problem, being that most vote totals seemed to be exactly twice
what the flash site claimed they were. Finally, I realized that there
was a master 'total votes' line for each candidate which made most of
the hacks and shims I had written into my scraper obsolete. Instead, I
could simply show only this total line and everything would be right
again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was an amazing experience, especially how the work I was doing was
being picked up by people outside of RIT. Having to think fast on my
feet was a new one too. I, like most programmers, usually like to
examine a problem in detail and have time to test theories before
publishing changes. Here, I was coding just about as fast as I could to
fix each bug that turned up, and we managed to make it work before the
last precincts rolled in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even more than that, this was an opportunity to take the skills and
tools I've been accumulating through my time at RIT and make them do
something more than just a class assignment. This wasn't just another
program to be written and forgotten, this was something that represented
the school to some of the public who perhaps hadn't heard about what
we're doing here. And that is cool.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="FOSS@RIT"></category><category term="journalism"></category><category term="election"></category></entry><entry><title>Election Night</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/fossrit/election-night.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-03-29T02:59:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T15:50:42-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2011-03-29:/fossrit/election-night.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So election night is tonight. I'll have free time soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main reason for my lack of time lately has to do with the election.
On Wednesday, just before I was going to classes, I got a call from Remy
asking what my schedule was and if I'd like to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So election night is tonight. I'll have free time soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main reason for my lack of time lately has to do with the election.
On Wednesday, just before I was going to classes, I got a call from Remy
asking what my schedule was and if I'd like to take a trip to WXXI to
talk with Rachel Ward and at their election coverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few hours later, we're in the lobby of WXXI, being mistaken for
musicians (as anyone who meets Remy for the first time is likely to do),
and waiting for Rachel to come down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We took a quick tour of the facilities, met a few other people, and got
down to business. Monroe County's Board of Elections hosts a server with
the live election information on a static ip and takes it down once the
election is done. Further, this information is released in the form of
a flash app, making it harder to move the information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a short discussion, we decided that we weren't going to get
anywhere without making a call to the BoE. Rachel did her magic on the
phone, getting more information out of them than I ever could have done.
To make a long story short, this flash application is driven by an XML
file (actually two) and that the system was provided by the company who
made the machines and was pretty much a black box as far as they were
concerned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A short bit of Googling later, I had identified another location that
used these machines: London, Ontario. using their XML files as a base, I
made a quick scraper that spat out a basic table of races and
candidates. It wasn't pretty, but it worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the next few days, I poked and prodded at it, adding features and
eventually moving to an HTML output and checking against a few more
locations, and cleaned up the code some more. We met with Rachel once
more yesterday, set the site up to be running on innovationtrail.org,
and started the countdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current version of the scraper is now running on
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://foss.rit.edu/election/"&gt;http://foss.rit.edu/election/&lt;/a&gt; and should update its information every 30
seconds, once information exists.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="FOSS@RIT"></category><category term="journalism"></category><category term="election"></category></entry><entry><title>Another Blog</title><link href="http://blog.katherineca.se/meta/another-blog.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-09-07T16:49:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T14:07:06-05:00</updated><author><name>Katherine Case</name></author><id>tag:blog.katherineca.se,2010-09-07:/meta/another-blog.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Just as I get used to this one, another of my classes requires me to
keep a blog, and to keep it separate from any other blogs we may keep.
The new blog is linked at left, but anything interesting will get
cross-posted here and it's likely going to go …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Just as I get used to this one, another of my classes requires me to
keep a blog, and to keep it separate from any other blogs we may keep.
The new blog is linked at left, but anything interesting will get
cross-posted here and it's likely going to go unmaintained at the
conclusion of the quarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here it is: &lt;a class="reference external" href="other-person.tumblr.com"&gt;other-person.tumblr.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="meta"></category><category term="journalism"></category></entry></feed>