<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Why Not Wingnut?</title><link href="http://nathanielca.se/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://nathanielca.se/feeds/tag/jquery.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://nathanielca.se/</id><updated>2013-06-02T03:18:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>National Day of Civic Hacking</title><link href="http://nathanielca.se/fossrit/national-day-of-civic-hacking.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-06-02T03:18:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel Case</name></author><id>tag:nathanielca.se,2013-06-02:fossrit/national-day-of-civic-hacking.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the projects I worked on during the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hackforchange.org/fossrit-rochester-civic-hackathon"&gt;Rochester edition&lt;/a&gt; of the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hackforchange.org"&gt;National Day of Civic Hacking&lt;/a&gt; hackathon was not actually anything intended
for the hackathon, but a short project I wrote last summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you remember from &lt;a class="reference external" href="introducing-fossrit-timeline-year-in-review.html"&gt;my last post&lt;/a&gt; on the subject, I had made three files,
one for each of the years that the FOSSBox had been keeping track of its
activities on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://foss.rit.edu/timeline"&gt;timeline&lt;/a&gt;. The files were very silly- all the data was
loaded on the fly from a JSON file, so the only thing in the files was the structure and the 'decoration' text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly this was not something that could stand. Today I finally managet to get
all the files together into one page. Now, when the page loads, it scans the
JSON file for all years mentioned, and populates a drop-down list with all the
years it has found. the first (and usually latest) year's data is then loaded
onto the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the user clicks on another year from the list, the content is reloaded with
data from the apropriate year. If you want to see it in action, the new review
page for timeline now lives &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://foss.rit.edu/timeline/summary.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="hackathon"></category><category term="timeline"></category><category term="jQuery"></category></entry><entry><title>Introducing: FOSS@RIT Timeline Year in Review</title><link href="http://nathanielca.se/fossrit/introducing-fossrit-timeline-year-in-review.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-08-22T22:15:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel Case</name></author><id>tag:nathanielca.se,2012-08-22:fossrit/introducing-fossrit-timeline-year-in-review.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I sat down with Remy and went over the last of the things we
need to do to close out the summer. There was a long list of items,
split into two sections, each containing the same sort of stuff.
FOSS&amp;#64;RIT has done a lot of stuff in the past year, and we need to be
able to tell people about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first section concerned the few things we had done that hadn't yet
hit &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://foss.rit.edu/timeline/"&gt;Timeline&lt;/a&gt;. This was a fairly sizable chunk of things, and we
needed a good, rapid-entry way of getting more events in there. No
problem, I had done some work on that before, I could get it running and
dump events in there no problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second (and slightly longer) list dealt with things we needed to
compile some information about as a sort of &amp;quot;here's what we've done&amp;quot;
report. The list of things that needed to be in that was... just about
the same as the last one. Remy planned to go through the Timeline site
and add entries from it, categorize them, and push it to foss.rit.edu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This deeply concerned me on two distinct levels. First was the part of
me that never liked writing. I've mentioned it here once before, and I
feel I've gotten better since then, but the concept of wading through
all that data to write a report was not something that made me happy.
The other part was that all the things in the second list had to be
added to the timeline at some point anyway, or were likewise available
from other sources. When Remy showed me what he had written for 2010, it
was obvious this could be easily replicated in code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About an hour of JavaScript wrangling later, I had made &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://foss.rit.edu/timeline/2011.html"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. Also
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://foss.rit.edu/timeline/2010.html"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, and if you're reading this from about a year in the future,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://foss.rit.edu/timeline/2012.html"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; should even exist. It's still needs some tweaking, the years are
hardcoded in the documents, the pages aren't linked from the main
timeline page, and I'd rather have them all use one common file than
make a new one each year, but it works, it's fairly similar to what was
handwritten last year, and it gets updated every time something gets
added to Timeline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="data alchemy"></category><category term="jQuery"></category><category term="timeline"></category></entry></feed>