<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Why Not Wingnut?</title><link href="http://nathanielca.se/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://nathanielca.se/feeds/tag/lemonade.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://nathanielca.se/</id><updated>2011-05-08T03:16:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Imagine RIT 2011</title><link href="http://nathanielca.se/fossrit/imagine-rit-2011.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-05-08T03:16:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel Case</name></author><id>tag:nathanielca.se,2011-05-08:fossrit/imagine-rit-2011.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I've been absent for a while lately, but with good reason. I've been
preparing for Imagine RIT, which was held earlier today.
After pulling possibly my longest day's hack yesterday (1pm to 4am,
approximately), I woke up at 9 and headed over to the Innovation Center
to talk to people about FOSS. All day long, the FOSSBox was filled with
curious people, looking to find out what it is we did. We had kids
poking around on the OLPCs, checking out our software, and occasionally
getting lost opening new programs. Every time I finished showing a group
around all the different projects hosted in the FOSSBox, a brand new
group would appear and start asking questions. It was tiring, especially
on about three hours of sleep, but it was quite fun and exciting showing
off our work to new people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of particular interest was Lemonade Stand, which seemed to excite many
of the children who came around. Most seemed to pick up the game with
minimal instruction (though it helped that by now I know very well which
areas to explain... they should get tightened in the future) and most
had lots of fun despite the large quantities of math involved.
And the backdrop to all this was &lt;a class="reference external" href="rise.rit.edu"&gt;Rise Above the Crowd&lt;/a&gt;, the project I
was spending so much time polishing yesterday. I don't know if I could
explain what exactly Rise is, other than a real-time journalism and news
collection framework, which doesn't really explain anything. Basically,
users submit stories and photos to Rise, which in turn keep track of
popular and recent content and display this information to strategically
placed screens throughout the campus. After a few hiccoughs, the servers
were online and serving data to the public, who then voted on their
favorite stories. At the FOSSBOX, we had the projector set up serving
the HD display mode so people could see what was current while they were
there. Since I was the one most familiar with the system at the time, I
tried to field any questions that popped up at the time to the best of
my knowledge, though sometimes that wasn't much help. As the day
progressed, we uncovered a few new bugs in the new system, and have some
new tasks before the final release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, a very exciting and fun weekend. We made a few contacts,
introduced a few more people to FOSS&amp;#64;RIT, and gave away at least 40
LiveCDs. I think that qualifies as quite a success.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="journalism"></category><category term="lemonade"></category><category term="sugar"></category><category term="Rise"></category><category term="OPL"></category></entry><entry><title>Lemonade Stand 2.1 Released</title><link href="http://nathanielca.se/fossrit/lemonade-stand-21-released.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-11-12T07:03:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel Case</name></author><id>tag:nathanielca.se,2010-11-12:fossrit/lemonade-stand-21-released.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am proud to announce the immediate availability of Lemonade Stand 2.1,
with a quarter's worth of work and effort behind it.
There are few gameplay changes in this release, but it feels like a
brand new game thanks to the wonderful new art assets courtesy of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jtmengel.blogspot.com/"&gt;JT&lt;/a&gt;.
There's also the beginning of a help system, and many generalizations in
the code to make adding new features even easier than before.
We're a little late for a midnight release, but for my first real game
release, I don't think we did half bad.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://activities.sugarlabs.org/en-US/sugar/addon/4321"&gt;http://activities.sugarlabs.org/en-US/sugar/addon/4321&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="lemonade"></category></entry><entry><title>Lemonade Recap</title><link href="http://nathanielca.se/fossrit/lemonade-recap.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-11-10T20:26:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel Case</name></author><id>tag:nathanielca.se,2010-11-10:fossrit/lemonade-recap.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So here we are at the end of the quarter. Have we accomplished our
goals? I think so.
We've gotten a lot done in the last ten weeks. We got some new images,
we got some new ideas into the game, and on the whole, it looks much
better. The game is slowly taking shape into something people might
actually want to play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;But let's compare what we've actually done to our goals. The first goal
was to get an updated background image with prettier graphics that
changed with the weather. This is definitely done, and has been for a
week or two. We've since invented a few more graphics that need to be
included in the main screen, but the placeholders we have should do for
now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Second, we wanted to get a graphical store in place and working. That's
almost done, and should be finished before the end of the week. The
store is fully functional, it just needs a few tweaks and some feedback
on the user's current inventory. For the time being that can be fixed
until we can get a more permanent solution later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, the overlooked problem we were ignoring this whole time, an in
game help system. This is moving along, not well, but it should be
functional by our release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="lemonade"></category></entry><entry><title>Lemonade Week... 8?</title><link href="http://nathanielca.se/fossrit/lemonade-week-8.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-10-26T23:59:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel Case</name></author><id>tag:nathanielca.se,2010-10-26:fossrit/lemonade-week-8.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So... lots of stuff has happened in the last few weeks.
First, we have a new background, thanks to JT. In fact, we have three
now, and as of five minutes ago, a different one will show up depending
on the current weather.
There's also been a lot of behind-the-scenes updates to make adding new
events and weather types easier in the future. Generally, all that kind
of stuff goes in constants.py, but that might have to change if we need
to add too much more stuff.
We've got a few exciting ideas we hope to get done in the next few
weeks, and I look forward to seeing what we can get done.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="lemonade"></category><category term="sugar"></category></entry><entry><title>Lemons Taking Off</title><link href="http://nathanielca.se/fossrit/lemons-taking-off.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-09-23T14:35:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel Case</name></author><id>tag:nathanielca.se,2010-09-23:fossrit/lemons-taking-off.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It looks like Lemonade Stand is taking off for fall quarter's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://teachingopensource.org/index.php/RIT/The_Course"&gt;HFOSS&lt;/a&gt;
class. This is quite exciting and there's a number of things I'm looking
to get in for a 2.2 release
* More events
* Fluctuating prices
* Loyalty and advertising
among &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wiki.sugarlabs.org/go/Lemonade_Stand#Additional_Ideas_.26_Features"&gt;others&lt;/a&gt;.
The 2.1 release, meanwhile, I would like to focus on usability and
graphics, as those have been being worked on for the longest so far.
Whether any of this will work out the way I'm imagining is debatable,
but I've got a plan and two &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://smw-os.blogspot.com/"&gt;awesome&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jtmengel.blogspot.com"&gt;people&lt;/a&gt; working on it with me&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="lemonade"></category><category term="sugar"></category></entry><entry><title>Refreshing Lemonade</title><link href="http://nathanielca.se/fossrit/refreshing-lemonade.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-09-23T14:04:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel Case</name></author><id>tag:nathanielca.se,2010-09-23:fossrit/refreshing-lemonade.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In other news, yesterday marked the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.jlewopensource.com/2010/07/lemonade-stand-release.html"&gt;final release of Lemonade
Stand 2.0&lt;/a&gt;. Now running on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fedorahosted.org/fortune_hunter/wiki/FortuneEngine"&gt;Fortune Engine&lt;/a&gt; and containing 0% of
my code, this marks an important milestone in my open-source
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sugarlabs.org/"&gt;sugar-based&lt;/a&gt; lemonade stand game as it's still getting developed!
While I can claim none of the credit for the code, it is still
satisfying to watch my very first open source project still on its feet,
teetering around like a drunken toddler.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="lemonade"></category><category term="sugar"></category></entry></feed>