<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Why Not Wingnut?</title><link href="http://qalthos.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://qalthos.github.io/blog/feeds/tag/python.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://qalthos.github.io/blog/</id><updated>2013-06-01T20:46:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>A note on lxml</title><link href="http://qalthos.github.io/blog/a-note-on-lxml.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-06-01T20:46:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel Case</name></author><id>tag:qalthos.github.io/blog,2013-06-01:a-note-on-lxml.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post is being written from the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hackforchange.org/fossrit-rochester-civic-hackathon"&gt;Rochester edition&lt;/a&gt; of the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hackforchange.org"&gt;National Day of Civic Hacking&lt;/a&gt; hackathon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been doing a lot of things with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pygal.org"&gt;pygal&lt;/a&gt; lately. It's a really neat tool
for making SVG graphs in python. One 'problem' is that it needs &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lxml.de"&gt;lxml&lt;/a&gt;, and
that has C extensions that need to be compiled. This isn't too bad, though
sometimes it makes me stop and install a compiler. The real problem is the
external header files it needs to compile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOTE: this blog post is entirely the result of my own laziness. Had I simply
perused the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lxml.de/installation.html#installation"&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;, I would have found this much sooner. Thus, this
post is solely a marker of my own eagerness to get things running quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I was asked for the third time how to install lxml, I finally decided I
would figure out how it works so it could be done properly. I did find out
what the needed package was, but I also found that if the shell variable
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;STATIC_DEPS=true&lt;/tt&gt; was set prior to installation, lxml would seek out and
download its requirements for you. I don't know how legitimate this is for a
Python install, but it was certainly quite useful for me and the others
trying to use lxml. It even works inside a virtualenv, though I don't know why
it wouldn't.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="hackathon"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="wat"></category></entry></feed>