<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Why Not Wingnut?</title><link href="http://nathanielca.se/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://nathanielca.se/feeds/tag/sugar.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://nathanielca.se/</id><updated>2013-08-05T02:04:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Building a Schoolserver</title><link href="http://nathanielca.se/fossrit/building-a-schoolserver.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-08-05T02:04:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel Case</name></author><id>tag:nathanielca.se,2013-08-05:fossrit/building-a-schoolserver.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of my tasks for this summer has been to try and get the FOSSBox's
schoolserver up and running again. We previouly had one a number of years ago,
but the hardware failed some time ago and the system itself was running a
hacked-together Debian build and did not have access to some of the actual
schoolserver scripts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first attempted to run the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wiki.laptop.org/go/XS_Installing_Software_0.7"&gt;instructions&lt;/a&gt; for the latest proper release of
the XO Schoolserver (henceforth XS), but this did not end very well. For one,
the instructions (and many automated scripts) assume you have two network
cards: one for the internal LAN to which the XO laptops connect, and another
connecting to the Internet. This assumption that the XS would be the gateway
device for a network of XO laptops would be fine in most deployments where
there is no existing infrastructure to get in the way, but at RIT where there
is not only significant infrastructure, but infrastructure I cannot easily
modify or control, it is less applicable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the steps I have taken to turn a fresh CentOS/RHEL server into an XS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set up &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/EPEL"&gt;EPEL&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wiki.laptop.org/go/XS_Installing_Software_0.7#Installing_on_top_of_existing_OS_installation"&gt;OLPC-XS repository&lt;/a&gt; to your yum config.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;yum install ejabberd idmgr &lt;span class="pre"&gt;ds-backup-server&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;xs-activity-server&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;xs-domain-config&lt;/span&gt; &amp;lt;domain name&amp;gt;&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;xs-setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;system-config-firewall-tui&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; to unblock ports 22, 80, 8080, 5222, 5223,
and 4369&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;xs-setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; is the most trying of the commands, because it does a lot of
background work to set up the OLPC versions of many config files (while still
leaing the originals in place).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's more to it, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;xs-setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; tends to have some annoying side effects,
some of the config files need to be manually updated, but this is the general
idea. This post will be further updated as time goes on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main problem seen so far is that this is being set up on a RHEL server
backed by XEN, and the OLPC-XS repository keeps wanting to install an
incompatible kernel, hosing the system on a regular basis.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="sugar"></category><category term="schoolserver"></category></entry><entry><title>Imagine RIT 2011</title><link href="http://nathanielca.se/fossrit/imagine-rit-2011.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-05-08T03:16:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel Case</name></author><id>tag:nathanielca.se,2011-05-08:fossrit/imagine-rit-2011.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I've been absent for a while lately, but with good reason. I've been
preparing for Imagine RIT, which was held earlier today.
After pulling possibly my longest day's hack yesterday (1pm to 4am,
approximately), I woke up at 9 and headed over to the Innovation Center
to talk to people about FOSS. All day long, the FOSSBox was filled with
curious people, looking to find out what it is we did. We had kids
poking around on the OLPCs, checking out our software, and occasionally
getting lost opening new programs. Every time I finished showing a group
around all the different projects hosted in the FOSSBox, a brand new
group would appear and start asking questions. It was tiring, especially
on about three hours of sleep, but it was quite fun and exciting showing
off our work to new people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of particular interest was Lemonade Stand, which seemed to excite many
of the children who came around. Most seemed to pick up the game with
minimal instruction (though it helped that by now I know very well which
areas to explain... they should get tightened in the future) and most
had lots of fun despite the large quantities of math involved.
And the backdrop to all this was &lt;a class="reference external" href="rise.rit.edu"&gt;Rise Above the Crowd&lt;/a&gt;, the project I
was spending so much time polishing yesterday. I don't know if I could
explain what exactly Rise is, other than a real-time journalism and news
collection framework, which doesn't really explain anything. Basically,
users submit stories and photos to Rise, which in turn keep track of
popular and recent content and display this information to strategically
placed screens throughout the campus. After a few hiccoughs, the servers
were online and serving data to the public, who then voted on their
favorite stories. At the FOSSBOX, we had the projector set up serving
the HD display mode so people could see what was current while they were
there. Since I was the one most familiar with the system at the time, I
tried to field any questions that popped up at the time to the best of
my knowledge, though sometimes that wasn't much help. As the day
progressed, we uncovered a few new bugs in the new system, and have some
new tasks before the final release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, a very exciting and fun weekend. We made a few contacts,
introduced a few more people to FOSS&amp;#64;RIT, and gave away at least 40
LiveCDs. I think that qualifies as quite a success.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="journalism"></category><category term="lemonade"></category><category term="sugar"></category><category term="Rise"></category><category term="OPL"></category></entry><entry><title>pyDex on Sugar</title><link href="http://nathanielca.se/personal/pydex-on-sugar.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-01-19T23:51:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel Case</name></author><id>tag:nathanielca.se,2011-01-19:personal/pydex-on-sugar.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A warning, this gets very technical with lots of acronyms and jargon.
tl;dr: I have a new pyDex branch which *should* run on the OLPC
A few days ago, I decided I'd finally see how well pyDex runs on the
OLPC. Turns out, it runs pretty well, which isn't too surprising as it
is written in pure pyGTK and Glade, both of which are well supported in
Sugar.
So today, I loaded up my dev files and set to work. First, though, I had
to clean up my dev branch and finish committing the few hacks I had
accumulated over the last few months. I finally fixed the zero index bug
and found I had a problem in my new scraper that was causing all the
evolution problems. In any case, that's all fixed, so my dev branch is
nice and clean and almost ready for the Black/White release in a few
weeks.
Getting back to Sugar, I finally found &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://magazine.redhat.com/2007/04/26/building-the-xo-porting-a-pygtk-game-to-sugar-part-two/"&gt;a good tutorial&lt;/a&gt; on *porting*
a pyGTK program rather than writing a new one. While admittedly I
haven't looked very hard, I had had a bit of a problem getting past the
example activity before, probably due to my use of Glade as I cannot
replace my top window as easily when it is automatically pulled from
Glade's XML and I really don't feel like defining everything in code.
The most useful thing I found in this tutorial is sending different
parents to the main panel depending on where it is called from. So if we
call the program normally, main_window is still loaded from Glade, but
if Sugar loads it, we use their prebuilt panel.
It still needs to be tested, and I need to add actual activity
information (and an icon eventually), but I think it should work. I'll
probably get to test it sometime this weekend, maybe even turn it into a
real activity by then. This is still just a small project, and I doubt
it will ever go up on Sugar's activities site, but it has given me a
much better understanding about how non-pygame activities work.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="sugar"></category><category term="pyDex"></category></entry><entry><title>Lemonade Week... 8?</title><link href="http://nathanielca.se/fossrit/lemonade-week-8.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-10-26T23:59:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel Case</name></author><id>tag:nathanielca.se,2010-10-26:fossrit/lemonade-week-8.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So... lots of stuff has happened in the last few weeks.
First, we have a new background, thanks to JT. In fact, we have three
now, and as of five minutes ago, a different one will show up depending
on the current weather.
There's also been a lot of behind-the-scenes updates to make adding new
events and weather types easier in the future. Generally, all that kind
of stuff goes in constants.py, but that might have to change if we need
to add too much more stuff.
We've got a few exciting ideas we hope to get done in the next few
weeks, and I look forward to seeing what we can get done.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="lemonade"></category><category term="sugar"></category></entry><entry><title>Lemons Taking Off</title><link href="http://nathanielca.se/fossrit/lemons-taking-off.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-09-23T14:35:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel Case</name></author><id>tag:nathanielca.se,2010-09-23:fossrit/lemons-taking-off.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It looks like Lemonade Stand is taking off for fall quarter's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://teachingopensource.org/index.php/RIT/The_Course"&gt;HFOSS&lt;/a&gt;
class. This is quite exciting and there's a number of things I'm looking
to get in for a 2.2 release
* More events
* Fluctuating prices
* Loyalty and advertising
among &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wiki.sugarlabs.org/go/Lemonade_Stand#Additional_Ideas_.26_Features"&gt;others&lt;/a&gt;.
The 2.1 release, meanwhile, I would like to focus on usability and
graphics, as those have been being worked on for the longest so far.
Whether any of this will work out the way I'm imagining is debatable,
but I've got a plan and two &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://smw-os.blogspot.com/"&gt;awesome&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jtmengel.blogspot.com"&gt;people&lt;/a&gt; working on it with me&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="lemonade"></category><category term="sugar"></category></entry><entry><title>Refreshing Lemonade</title><link href="http://nathanielca.se/fossrit/refreshing-lemonade.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-09-23T14:04:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel Case</name></author><id>tag:nathanielca.se,2010-09-23:fossrit/refreshing-lemonade.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In other news, yesterday marked the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.jlewopensource.com/2010/07/lemonade-stand-release.html"&gt;final release of Lemonade
Stand 2.0&lt;/a&gt;. Now running on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fedorahosted.org/fortune_hunter/wiki/FortuneEngine"&gt;Fortune Engine&lt;/a&gt; and containing 0% of
my code, this marks an important milestone in my open-source
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sugarlabs.org/"&gt;sugar-based&lt;/a&gt; lemonade stand game as it's still getting developed!
While I can claim none of the credit for the code, it is still
satisfying to watch my very first open source project still on its feet,
teetering around like a drunken toddler.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="lemonade"></category><category term="sugar"></category></entry></feed>